

SHALEM RAJ SINGH RAJPUT

MORE ABOUT ME

I am a self-taught Django developer with a bachelors degree, specializing in Backend Development. I have always found coding intuitive and have pushed myself to learn and pursue it as a career. As someone who enjoys finding solutions to difficult problems, transforming ideas into reality, web development was an obvious path.

I'm a fast learner and can quickly integrate into a team providing value to the company & the customer with the knowledge I have

TECHNICAL SKILLS

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGE

WEB TECHNOLOGIES

HTML, CSS, AJAX, XML

TOOLS AND FRAMEWORKS

- Django
- · Visual Studio
- Django REST Pycharm
- Jupyter Notebook

DATABASES

RDBMS • MySQL

NOSQL • MongoDB

COURSES & ACHIEVEMENTS

- Python Data Structures & Algorithms, Coding Ninjas
- Python skilled 4 star, Hackerrank
- · 30 Days of Code, Hackerrank

SOCIAL

- in https://linkedin.com/in/shalem-raj-singh-rajput-5b4843140
- https://github.com/rshalem
- imshalem.herokuapp.com

CONTACT DETAILS

- +91-8195888639
- shalem000@gmail.com

EDUCATION

Lovely Professional University

Bachelor of Technology, Mechanical Eng.

Secured overall 8.3 CGPA

WORK EXPERIENCE

WEB DEVELOPER, MACHINE LEARNING SPECIALIST

AMAZON, APPLIED MODELLING & DATA SCIENCE | Dec 2020-Present

DOMAIN DEFINITION/AUDIO FILE META-DATA API

- Working extensively on creating & testing RESTful APIs for Alexa Domain Definition, audio file server which would be used to map user requests to appropriate Domain & Intent for an user
- · Testing artifacts based on deterministic and statistical model. It's confidence score of routing to exact mapped Domain helping AIs Natural Language Understanding capabilities.

COMMUNITY PLATFORM PROJECT

- · Developed a user-friendly architecture that focuses on mitigating roadblocks & queries across
- · Responsible for developing, implementing and maintaining mostly internal web applications. I collaborated with technical and business staff in the design, development, testing, implementation and production support of enterprise applications using Django as the framework for Backend & HTML/CSS for the Frontend.
- Working with Python ORM Libraries including Django ORM

NATURAL LANGUAGE UNDERSTANDING FEATURE ARTIFACTS

- Working on building & testing Natural Language Understanding (NLU) components.
- Writing & testing grammars for NLU models to understand different artifacts and map to correct NLU routing for a particular request.

SENIOR MACHINE LEARNING ASSOCIATE

AMAZON | June 2017-December 2020

- · Developed Backend of a GUI along with another developer that focuses on compiling various automation scripts for multiple tasks in a single app structure
- Performed cleansing operation on data generated by Feature team with automated scripts in Python
- Worked in Annotation and Automated Speech Recognition (ASR) team to convert regular speech to Machine Understandable form, segregating the intent of the speech and help them route to the correct Domain with mapped Slot labels to provide required result and testing them
- Worked as an integral member of the Success Rate team to deep dive into critical nonfunctioning areas, and coming up with ways to resolve them.

PROJECTS

MOOD BASED WEB APP | FEBRUARY 2021 - PRESENT

Quora for Mood, user have the option to scroll through articles based on his/her mood and to explore how other people see it as. User has the ability to share across social media, leave a comment, all powered through AJAX. If user likes any article he/she can buy the author a coffee. Even chat with the author. Custom user signup & login enabling strong authentication. Frontend created using HTML for providing the structure & JQuery for AJAX, And Backend powered by Django and database for storage with SQLite and later DRF to be implemented for API creation as project grows.

LINKIFY | AUGUST 2020

One link for many links website backed up by Django Rest Framework for the creation of API for users & their links, authenticating every new and old users via Token Authentication. Features customizable User profiles. Each request is made through AJAX to eliminate the page reloading. SOLite is been used as the database to store all users & their social links.

CODERS COMMUNITY PLATFORM | MAY 2020

Developed a place for coders to share their insights & knowledge, any challenges or qurery where it lets you create an account via OAuth or simple registration. Each registered user can write, edit their own blog post & customize their profile where Signals make sure a user profile is created automatically when a new user registers. AJAX handles all comments, like functionality and form submission

SMART RESTAURANT APP | MAY-PRESENT

Working along with two more team member for a startup project, this app/website let's you choose your restaurant, book table as you go, order your food simply by a click.
Each Hotel provider are associated with this app providing their details which is stored in

MongoDB as our NoSQL database. APIs are built using DRF for every respective domain keeping in mind the mobile device interaction. All datas are fetched through API irrespective of the device that you are using.

COVID-19 TRACKER | MARCH-APRIL 2020

Designed and developed a web application to show real-time statistics of COVID-19 along with an inbuilt essentials & resources search functionality based on location written in Javascript. All the datas are fetched via APIs & is built using Django as backend & Bootstrap for Frontend.